Welcome to the teaching and
supernatural ministry of Pastor
Henry Oduwale, Lead Pastor of
Saviors Assembly International.
Galatians chapter 3, verse 2.
When you read about God's
promise to Abraham,
God's promise under the Old
Covenant. The fulfillment of
all the promises of God is in
the giving of the Spirit. So
there are many scriptures that
talked about the giving of the
Spirit, God pouring out his
Spirit upon all flesh. God puts
in his spirit in the heart of
men and all that. And here God
told Zechariah, he said he's
going to pour out the spirit of
grace and supplication. And
anywhere God talks about the
giving of his spirit or the
promise of his spirit, he often
indicates a particular
ministry of the Holy Spirit. Or
what the Holy Spirit is going to
do in the life of his people.
Hallelujah! You know, he told
Ezekiel, he said that he's going
to take a stony heart out of
them and then he will give them
the heart of flesh. He said they
will give them the Spirit, and
what the Spirit is going to do
is that the Spirit is going to
enable them to walk according
to his will. The Spirit is going
to enable them. That is what we
call the fruit of the Spirit.
Hallelujah! But here God told
Zechariah, he said he will pour
his Spirit upon his people,
and then he gave a specific
description of what the Spirit
is going to accomplish. He said
the spirit of grace and
supplication. See, after me,
say the spirit of grace. Hey,
louder, say the spirit of grace
and supplication. So it means
that the ministry of the Holy
Spirit is going to cover the
prayer aspect of the believer's
life. You know, we, we take so
many things for granted as
believers, especially for those
who are filled with the spirit.
And you know,
David looked into our day. I
know what he said. He said,
blessed is the man unto whom God
will not impute sin. He said,
blessed are those whose sins are
forgiven. So it means that why
you, you know, admire David's
work with God, is a man after
God's heart. David looked into
your days. And he said that, I
want, I desire what these people
have. Amen.
You know, it was Jesus was
talking to the Jews and he told
them, he said, see, greater than
Solomon is here. If I told you,
Solomon in all his glory was not
as clothed as this grass.
Hallelujah! Praise God! And what
is he saying? He's saying that
you have it better now than they
had it. Say after me, say, I
have it better now. Hey,
louder, say, I have it better
now. You know, when you read the
story of, you know, the prophets
and the patriarchs, the
encounter with God, you are
tempted to desire those kind of
encounter. Amen. Won't you
like to be the one walking
through the Red Sea on dry
ground? Amen. How many of you
will not mind eating manna for
40 years? I know many of you
because you like food. You don't
even understand the context.
Praise God. But you see, we have
it better in the New Covenant
than they had it under the Old
Covenant. Is that very clear?
Okay, so, so I was talking about
the promise of God. So he said
that I'm going to pour out the
spirit of grace and
supplication, and that is very
profound. It means that as
believers, you will never need
to struggle with your prayer
life. You know, the problem with
many Christians is that we like
what God promised in his word
But we do not pay attention to
how to come into the experience
of that promise. For example,
you say people like prosperity.
There's nobody that doesn't like
prosperity, but people don't
work in obedience.
Hallelujah! Praise God
forevermore!
Just like you, you like to have
a fervent prayer life, you would
love to be the kind of person
that every moment of your life
you are living it in prayer.
But you see, you need to
understand the way that God has
made available for that
possibility. So he told them,
he said, I will pour the spirit
of grace and supplication,
which means that One of the
expressions or the ministry of
the Holy Spirit in the lives of
my people is the enablement to
pray. Is that very clear?
Enablement to pray. In fact,
you know, Bible says that God
has given us the spirit
of sonship whereby we cry,
Abba, Father. So it means that
the cry of the believer is
enabled by the Spirit. Many
Christians are not conscious of
the presence and the ministry of
the Holy Spirit in their life,
and that is the sole reason why
many people are struggling. So
you need to understand that the
Christian life is designed to
be empowered by the Holy Spirit.
You are going to struggle in
your walk with God. You are
going to struggle in your prayer
life. You will struggle with
Bible study. You will struggle
with your entire Christian life
until you are conscious, you
practice the presence of God.
And practicing God's presence,
it simply means that you being
conscious of the presence of the
Holy Spirit in your life.
Amen. I'm driving out somewhere
this evening. Praise God
forevermore. Praise God
forevermore. So God said, I'm
going to pour out the spirit of
grace and supplication. So that
means as a believer, you will
not have to see— now pay
attention to me— anytime you
find yourself struggling Now,
the reason many people don't
have a prayer life is that they,
they struggle to pray. But then
you need to understand the
provision of God out of that
position. It is the Spirit. Is
that very clear? So God does not
want you to try to reach out to
him through your sheer human
efforts. He has made a way in
the Holy Ghost. Say, God has
made a way for me in
the Holy Ghost. He has given us
the Spirit. He said, whereby we
cry, Abba, Father. Now let me,
let me read some scriptures to
you so that you can, you know,
appreciate the ministry of the
Holy Spirit in your life as
believer. Let's see Romans
chapter 8, verse 26. Likewise
the Spirit also helps our
infirmities, for we know not
what we should pray for as we
ought, but the Spirit himself
maketh intercession for us with
groanings which cannot be
uttered. And he that searcheth
the hearts knoweth what is the
mind of the Spirit, because he
maketh intercession for the
saints according to the will of
God. Praying. Okay, sorry. So it
says he maketh intercession for
the saints according to what?
The will of God. So we see in
this text that prayer is meant
to be aided by the Holy Spirit.
Prayer is what is meant to be
aided by the Holy Spirit.
It says he helps our
infirmities. Now, the
infirmities here is not talking
about medical condition, all
right? It is talking about the
limitation of the man, the
limitation of the mind, the
limitation of the human
strengths, the limitation of the
human understanding. Praise God!
So Bible says the Holy Spirit
helps this limitation. For we
know not what we should pray for
as we ought. We don't know what
we should pray for as we ought.
Amen. Oh, glory to God. Glory to
God. See, you owe it to God to
fulfill your purpose on earth.
You owe it to God to fulfill
your purpose on earth because
you have the Holy Spirit.
There's nobody— no believer
should have an excuse of not
having a robust prayer life.
A vibrant prayer life because
you have the Holy Spirit. He
says, this is one of the reasons
why I've given you the Spirit.
He is the Spirit of grace and
supplication. So he helps our
infirmities, he bears us up
in the time of weakness,
in a time of trouble. He helps
our inadequacy. He taketh all
together with us. Hallelujah!
He taketh all together with us.
Oh, praise God forevermore!
Ephesians chapter 6, verse 18.
Now I'm just laying foundation
for what I'm going to be
teaching this evening.
Ephesians 6:18: Praying
always with all prayer and
supplication in the spirit,
praying always with what? All
prayer and supplication in the
spirit. All prayer. Somebody say
all prayer, including the one
you pray in your bathroom,
including the one you pray in
the kitchen, plus the one you
pray behind the wheels when you
are driving. It says all prayer
in the spirit. So God— now
please pay attention to me— so
God never anticipates any moment
of your life or any moment of
prayer prayed without the aid of
the Holy Ghost. Are you getting
what I'm saying here? Okay, let
me repeat myself. God never
anticipates— God never expects
you to pray any prayer, whether
a casual— what you call a casual
prayer. You know, I've taught
you this, that as believers you
must learn how to place premium
on your prayer. As believer,
there's nothing like casual
prayer. Your 1-minute prayer can
work wonders. See, the potency
of your prayer has a lot to do
with the value, the weight you
place on it, the expectation,
the confidence in your heart
that this prayer will produce
results. Because for many
reasons, for many people, the
reason they are not seeing
results in their prayer life is
not even because they are not
praying well. Is it not because
they are not praying without the
consciousness? It is not because
they are praying without the
consciousness of the Holy
Spirit. It's not because they
are not following the principles
that govern prayer. The problem
is that they do not have
expectation. They do not place
premium on their prayer. I don't
have anything called casual
prayer. I've seen cripple walk
with casual prayer. I've seen
that they're risen back to life
with what you call casual
prayer. Because many times,
maybe, maybe the difference
between you and an anointed man
of God, all right, is the value
placed on prayer. And that is
why I tell you, if it occurs to
you that, hey, you've not been
praying, right there at that
moment, start praying. The
prayer you pray at that moment
is not less powerful, is not
less effective than the one you
pray when you clear your
schedule. Are you getting what
I'm saying here? You may just be
able to generate more power,
but you know the interesting
thing? When Bible talks about
the tremendous power that is
made available, the
tremendousness of that power is
not primarily in volume. It is
in the essence and the nature of
that power. Because see, the
effectiveness of the things of
the spirit is is not measured by
volume. That's why when the
disciples said that, hey, pray
for us that our faith will
increase— see, this thing, the
peace of the Spirit, is not
primarily by volume.
It is you placing premium.
Are you getting what I'm saying?
Say, I have no casual prayer.
Praise God. Say, even my casual
prayer— louder— say, even my
casual prayer cause casualties
in the camp of the enemy.
There's nothing like casual
prayer. So Bible says, praying
all prayer, praying always,
always. That is the frequency of
your prayer. Then he said, all
prayer, all prayer.
Last week I taught you different
kinds of prayer. Praise God. I
taught you prayer of
intercession. I taught you
supplication. I taught you
prayer of inquiry, prayer of
consecration. I talked about
commanding prayer. Praise God
forevermore. And the other
prayer, I can't remember now.
Prayer, boy. Oh, worship. Thank
you very much. So you see, all
this prayer— he said you pray
all prayer in the spirit.
So it means that God never
expected you. He knows that you
have infirmity in your flesh.
He knows that you can wake up
without appetite for prayer. He
anticipated it.
Your low moment is not a shock
to God. God is not offended.
God is not grieved by your low
moment. He anticipated it, and
then he made provision in the
Holy Ghost. He said, I will give
you the spirit of grace and
supplication. Amen. You know the
reason many people don't have
effective prayer? Their prayer
is not generating enough impact.
It's because they have mental
picture. Of what powerful prayer
looks like. And devil likes that
mindset. Devil will keep using
the picture to guilt trip you,
and you can never rise to do
what you are— you can never rise
above what you are guilty of.
Have you struggled with a bad
habit and you really feel guilty
about it, but the feeling of
guilt never stops you from
repeating it? Devil just like
you to— he likes to guilt trip
you. So you have a mentor that
they told you the way, ah, the
way Alaba prayed. Amen. And then
we found out that some of those
stories were not even really
true. Of course, some are true,
but even if all the stories are
true, it was the spirit. I don't
want to get ahead of myself
because I'm still going to get
to that in this teaching. So you
need to understand I said
something, I think I did a
video, I don't know whether it
is out, that you see, as a
believer, you must learn to find
your rhythm in the spirit. Is
that very clear? You should
what? Find your rhythm. Now,
while you are trying to
discipline yourself to wake up
in the midnight to pray, don't
live in condemnation to now
think the one you pray in the
morning or afternoon is not
effective. Because now you see,
some folks will talk about, you
know, how we did 18 hours and
all that. And as I always say,
it is good for you to have such
discipline. You should have
moments where you just stretch
in the place of prayer. I'm
planning we're going to do that
in the month of September. If
you pick a prophecy I gave while
I was preaching, was it on
Sunday, that September we are
stretching, September we are
stretching. Because anytime you
receive a word on stretching,
let your first response be in
prayer. Because prayer is how we
stretch the borders of our
hearts. But then you see, you
must understand, now you will
agree with me that there was
actually nowhere in scripture
that shows that the apostles,
they prayed 24 hours at stretch.
Are you getting what I'm saying
here? Now what I am
communicating to you is this:
never allow the devil to guilt
trip you. You will never, you
will never see. It doesn't
matter your intention, you will
not be able to rise up in prayer
when you keep having guilt.
That's why I said that the
prayer of a righteous man— so
you need the consciousness of
that righteousness for you to
rise up. What condemnation
does is that it suppresses your
prayer life. Have you made up
your mind to pray for— then you
remember one bad thing you did,
maybe now you have better light.
Maybe when you were growing up
in faith and all that, you just
remember one bad thing that you
did, and right there is as if
they pour ice water on you, and
all your excitement, the passion
just got deflated. That's the
spirit of religion. Find your
reading and then grow with it.
Is that very clear?
Amen. All prayer
whole prayer. Whole prayer.
Louder. Say, whole prayer.
Whole prayer. I can't hear you.
Say, whole prayer. Whole prayer.
Whole prayer. A supplication. A
what? In the spirit. So one
of the ministries of the Holy
Spirit in your life is to supply
all the aids that you need to
pray. So God never expects you
to pray any prayer
Spirit. The reason many
Christians are struggling with
prayer is because they do not
have a conscious relationship.
Now, whether you are conscious
of the presence of the Holy
Spirit or not, you have a
relationship with him. But you
need to have a conscious
relationship with the Holy
Spirit, and that is what we call
the practice of God's presence.
And one of the things the
practice of the presence of the
Holy Spirit does is this: it
helps you to pray spontaneously.
Do you know they asked Smith
Wigglesworth? They said, sir,
please tell us. How many of you
know Smith Wigglesworth? Praise
God. I think we should be having
criteria to admit people for
hearing of faith. I don't know
if you know Smith Wigglesworth.
All right, now you hear the
amazing things that God did
through this man of God.
Amazing things. He raises the
dead as if he's waking people
from sleep. Now they asked him,
they said, please tell us your
spirit, tell us, tell us your
secrets, tell us your secrets.
We know that this thing can
never be possible without a
robust prayer life. Tell us your
prayer secrets. And he said that
I have never prayed more than 30
minutes, I've never prayed more
than 20 minutes at a time. In my
life, but there is no 20 minutes
that pass without me praying
because there's no formula to
this thing. Now, when we
encourage you to do a minimum of
1 hour in tongues daily, it is
to stretch, it is to exercise
yourself. Because the thing is
this: if you can do 1 hour
praying in tongues on daily
basis, it's just like you
exercising, you are doing
morning walk, morning jog, and
all that. Now if they tell you
that, hey, bandits is here, you
have the stamina. And see, that
you see danger does not mean
that you have the strength to
run. Yoruba has a saying that
a 4-in-1 crippled man will
not be a victim of war, because
before the one will come close,
he knows his condition. He would
have vanished. Amen. Praise God
forevermore. So you must learn
to find your rhythm. He said, I
have never prayed for more than
20 minutes. So if he says he has
never prayed for more than 20
minutes, that at a stretch he
prays under most 20 minutes.
Look at the great things that
God did with him. Oh, pastor is
saying that I cannot reduce my
prayer to 20 minutes. That's
your cup of tea.
Praise God. You know, I, I
remember when I just started out
in ministry, and then I, I
devoured— oh my God, I,
I've read virtually everything
that Kenneth Hagin ever wrote,
including manuscripts that
didn't go into publication. And
then I stumbled on one of his
books, and when he said that he
has never fasted for more than 3
days, I was angry. That God,
are you a racist? Why is it that
this thing is so easy for this
Oyinbo people but for us? See,
at that moment I began to pay
more attention to Oyinbo
minister, because if you listen
to an African pastor, they just
make this thing to look so lofty
you cannot attain it. It is
spiritual elitism. You know
Jesus said that greater works
than me— thank God that it was
not an African man. Jesus was
not an African man. You want to
raise the dead? You know what?
You know this thing now? You
want to raise the dead? Ah,
you will need to first do 12
hours, 6 months at stretch.
Then you had midnight to eat.
Then by then we know that you
are ready. You can't hear those—
how many people have been able
to see? You can never— you can
never motivate God's people to
do God's will by fear.
So in the days of thy power,
thy people shall be willing.
And then I read Benny Hinn.
Benny Hinn said almost the same
thing. I think he just said that
he has never done more than 3
hours. Did these people do it?
Is it that God have different
standard for us in Africa?
Because the story that me I hear
from— you have to do 40 days.
I, I attended— I think that the
max marathon I've done is 21,
above 21. Praise God. I wanted
to do 40, but I had God. How
many of you have locked yourself
up in the room and say that God
'If you don't appear to me, I
will die.' I've said it many
times and I came out alive.
Nobody will tell you, you'll be
the one that will.
Amen. Glory to God. So what
am I saying?
Whatever the level you have
presently, one thing you must do
away with to rise up on the
wings of the Spirit is
condemnation. And then find
your rhythm in prayer. Because
one thing that many people don't
understand is this, you know,
God said that he gives the
spirit of grace and
supplication. See, these things
are in measures though. There
are some people that the
assignment, what God wants to
use them for, for example, you
have table knife Then you have
kitchen knife. Then there is the
one that butchers use. Then
there are those that doctors
use. Different degree of
sharpness. Now there are some
people, because of the kind of
assignment that God have for
Apostle Ayo Babalola, there is a
certain dimension of engine that
God puts on the inside of him
that you don't need. Those are
those here in the realm of the
spirit, they are bulldozers.
You know what they call dozers?
They are bulldozers. Their
assignment is to uproot Iroko
trees. Now you that your
assignment is to wither the
small, small grass, your own one
is not less important in the
kingdom. You say, ah, Apostle
Ayobabala, this man, and really
that man has a very strong
prayer life. Imagine they hand
over a microphone to you for you
to just close close a prayer
meeting and then you close it
for 3 days. That's not normal.
Amen. Praise God.
But you, you can't cook such
thing up. You will have to be
energized by a spirit. The same
thing is applicable to fasting.
Every single time people did 40
days fasting in scripture, it
was not out of sheer will. It is
not a formula. They were done
with it, and then they realized
that they have done 40 days.
Because God will have to release
the spirit of grace and
supplication. Are you following
what I'm saying? So he says,
all prayer— say after me, say
all prayer. L say all prayer and
supplication in the spirit, in
the spirit, watching thereunto
with all perseverance and
supplication for all saints. So
the reason we encourage you to
have certain hours of prayer,
on the minimum you pray daily,
is for you to maximize what you
have in Christ Jesus. It is for
you to exercise yourself in the
things of the spirit, because
the matter will come up that
will require you to tarry in the
place of prayer. If you have not
exercised yourself consistently
on daily basis, you will not— if
you stained in the days of
adversity, your strength is
small. So all of this is just to
build a system that will enable
you to grow. Praise God
forevermore. Jude 20 says,
but ye, beloved, building up
yourselves on your most holy
faith, praying in what? In the
flesh? In the Holy Ghost. So you
see that every time God talks
about prayer in his word, it is
with the aid of the Spirit.
Now, when you are not conscious
of the ministry of the Holy
Spirit, then you struggle. Now,
my point is that prayer, right
from the Old Testament, when God
promised the Spirit, he let us
understand that he is going to
come with the Spirit of grace
and supplication.
You see it in 1 Corinthians
chapter 14. Glory to God. It
says, now what is it then? How
we pray with the Spirit and how
we pray with understanding also.
When you are praying with the
Spirit, what is going on? It is
the Holy Spirit supplying
utterance, supplying utterance.
Praise God, praise God.
So all the scriptures shows us
one thing, that God never expect
you to have a prayer life. In
fact, he does not expect you to
have a prayer moment outside
the help of the Holy Spirit. So
what I want to teach you this
evening is how to respond to
the help of the Holy Spirit.
How to respond. You can learn
all kinds of prayer, you can
listen to all teachings, but if
you do not know how to respond
to the Spirit of grace and
supplication, you will still not
have a prayer life. Holy Spirit
enables us to pray. Two things
God said In that verse,
he said, 'They will give you the
spirit of one grace,' and
then supplication. This grace is
an enablement of the Holy
Spirit. Then supplication.
Now, what is supplication?
Supplication is an earnest
petition. Need to God.
Supplication,
it's emphasizing
the earnest, the fervency with
which you make your petition
known to God. Glory to God!
Heartfelt, heartfelt requests.
Glory to God! Asu vele menoko
sovai. Grandoku sovele
mangladike tsuzuvai. You see,
you, you can pray, you can pray
for let's say maybe 10 minutes
and generate more results than
you pray for 1 hour. What makes
the difference is how earnest
the prayer is. I think I once
thought on this when God sent
Isaiah to tell Hezekiah that he
should pack up, he's going to
die. And Bible says that Ezekiel
turned to the wall and he didn't
pray in tongues. He didn't pray
in tongues. He just— he just—
that is petition. Petition is a
specific request.
It's a specific request. That
specific request that you have,
that, oh God, I know one of
the reasons why I— and God
forbid that you end this year
without the prophecy of the
dream year not being fulfilled
in your life. Because see,
dream year is not a petition.
There must be something specific
that reflects the dream
prophecy. If the prayer is
vague, it is not a petition.
Now, for those who have written
petition to maybe the police
before, you know you have to be
specific on what you are writing
petition. Or somebody is trying
to claim your land, then you
will have to— in that petition,
you have to state where the land
is located, when you bought the
land. You will attach documents
that prove that you are the
rightful owner of the property.
Then you have to talk about what
they are doing to the land and
the specific thing you want the
government to intervene on. Is
that very clear? That is
petition. You know,
interestingly, you know, uh,
you know, uh, Paul was writing
to the church, said, see, be
anxious for nothing. He said,
but with what? Prayer and
supplication, with thanksgiving,
make your petition known unto
God. So there must be
specificity. That is what makes
it a petition. Father, bless me.
That's no petition.
Is that very clear? Oh, do you
know that the gift of the Holy
Ghost is the blessing of
Abraham? Oh, you didn't know
that? We will receive the
blessing of Abraham, which is
the Holy Spirit. Healing is a
blessing. Are you still there?
He said all spiritual blessings
in the heavenly places, but in
petition you've got to be
specific. And you see, the
reason many people pray a prayer
that is not heartfelt is because
there is no specificity on that
prayer. That's why you press.
Brodo koso bi hai. Father, as I
go out today, bless me, bless
me, bless me, bless me, bless
me, bless me. How?
He has already blessed you.
Isn't it? So a prayer for
blessing is not a petition. He
has already blessed you with all
spiritual blessings in the
heavenly places. So when you
just say, Father, bless me, you
are actually asking for what he
has already done. But now you
want an outworking of that
blessing in your life. Oh
Father, bless my family with a
new house. We desire a 5-bedroom
duplex. That is petition.
That is petition. Oh, thank you,
Lord Jesus. You've been writing
application, you are not getting
a favorable response, and you
tabled the matter before the
Lord. That is petition. And one
thing about petition is this:
you stay on it until you receive
an answer of peace. So petition
is the specific request The
heartfelt prayer you pray
regarding those things is the
supplication. Is that very
clear? So you cannot actually
separate supplication from what?
From petition. So supplication
is how you pray.
It is the intensity with which
you present your case before the
Lord. Glory to God! Thank you,
Holy Spirit! Thank you, Holy
Spirit. Thank you, Holy Spirit.
I want to just repeat this
again. God never intend,
design prayer to
be offered without the help of
the Holy Spirit. But are you
yielding to this help? Are you
yielding to the Holy Spirit?
That's why I say you, you must
never leave your day without
conscious awareness of the
presence of the Holy Spirit.
There's something about
awareness, it makes you to
respond. Now you, you can be in
a house, you can be in a room
with a snake, as long as you
don't know, you won't react to
it. I remember many years ago,
I was— my mom told me to go get
something. From a particular
spot in the room. And as I
lifted the basket, I saw a snake
coiled under the basket. I
bolted. So the,
the man that came to kill the
snake, he said, from the look of
things, this snake has actually
been here for a very long time,
but we never knew. The same
thing is applicable to the
things of the spirit. When you
are not conscious of of it, you
cannot respond to it. Some of
you thought that you are
prayerless, you don't, you don't
have a passion for prayer. It is
not true. You have— he
says he has given you the Spirit
whereby you cry. So it means you
can't cry without the Spirit.
Maybe I should run you through
how the Holy Spirit helps you in
prayer. I taught on this last
year during, uh, Rivers Camp
Meeting. Glory to God. The first
thing the Holy Spirit helps you
on in prayer is to prompt you to
pray. Praise God! The Holy
Spirit prompts you to pray. The
Spirit of God creates or awakens
the desire to pray. It
sensitizes you. It draws your
attention to matters that
require Urgent prayer.
It prompts us to pray. Now, it
doesn't matter how you feel
before the prompting comes. The
one who prompts you to pray is
the one that will supply the
grace and supplication. But he
said most times we miss this
ministry of the Holy Spirit
because we always look at
ourselves. We always look at
ourselves. It doesn't matter how
you felt. It doesn't matter the
feeling you have. Before the
prompting comes, all that God
requires from you is to just
yield. He will take it up from
there. Just yield.
Sometimes you can just even say,
Holy Spirit, I know you want me
to pray. I'm feeling so weak.
I'm feeling so fatigued. I don't
feel like— please help me. Help
me. And stay there. If you tell
him to help you, you don't walk
away. Just stay there. The man
of God asked Pastor Adeboye, he
said, please, can you just give
me insight into your prayer
life? And Baba said that
sometimes I am just in God's
presence, and all I could just
muster is Jesus, Jesus,
Jesus, Jesus. Jesus,
Jesus. Bible says the name of
the Lord is a strong tower. Oh,
some of you don't even
understand that if Jesus is the
only thing that you can say,
you don't understand that. See,
sometimes God abeg can mean
different thing. Ah, you don't
know. See, the one who have 20
prayer points but just pray,
that's why sometimes it's— you
can almost think that I am
discouraging prayer points.
Because, because many times when
you are prayer point oriented
with your prayer life, you will
miss a lot. In fact, the one
that said God, I beg endlessly.
I remember one time I learned
this lesson from someone on a
mountain. You know, I, I think I
told you tonight I used to go on
mountain to pray, and then I was
praying not too far from this
guy, and this guy was just the
same prayer points. God have
mercy. The way he was saying is
as if he said that, God, I beg
God. And he stayed with that
prayer for days. Are you getting
what I'm saying here? It is
hellish. You see, all the things
you are calling, whatever you
are saying, you are conveying
thoughts. You are simply
convinced. So you don't have to
say the same thing a thousand
ways. Bible says that Jesus
kept going back after coming to
wake the disciples. Bible say he
went back to pray the same
thing. And I want to practice
this: when you have a serious
issue to deal with, learn to
pray a focused prayer, that even
if you have other things— now
that doesn't mean that you can
actually bombard God with so—
like you can confuse heaven when
your prayer point is too much.
It is not for sake of heaven,
it is for the sake of your own
earnest prayer. Like I said,
Christians can be so deluded.
Christians are the only ones you
will see who are not praying,
but they are surprised that
their life is the way it is. I
don't even know what is going
on. My job is not going the way
it is. My business— he is not
praying. He blames everything
but himself, and devil likes it.
So before you start complaining,
ask yourself, have I truly
prayed over this matter? We just
catch ourselves that it's as if
we have been having too much
conversation about this issue,
but we have not prayed about it.
But has never failed. I'm
telling you, this is one of the
ways the devil has robbed many
believers of the best that God
has for them. Devil will never
mind. He will not interfere in
your conversation about the
problem except the attempt to
pray about it. I stumbled on
this scripture, you know, one
time. Proverb— Proverb 19,
verse 3. Proverb 19, verse 3.
It says, the foolishness of a
person ruins his way. And his
heart rages against the Lord.
The NIV says, a person's own
folly leads to their own ruin,
yet their heart rages against
God. One translation says that
the foolishness of a man
destroys their life, then they
turn to blame God. Praise God!
So the Holy Spirit prompts us,
but you must learn how to
respond to this prompting. He
will pour out the Spirit of
grace and supplication. You must
learn how to respond to it. The
reason it looks as if you don't
have a prayer life, the reason
it looks as though you don't
pray when it hurts you, is
because you always rely on your
own strength. You always judge
that moment by how you feel.
There is supply, and I'm telling
you, the supply of God's Spirit
is epicuregia.
Amen. Oh, glory to God! How many
of you still remember that
teaching? My daughter was
sharing that message with me on—
I mean, yesterday on the dining.
I said, do you remember the
message you preached on
epikuridion? I was like, how can
you even be— I had to rehearse
the Greek word before I master
it, and you just say it casually
like that.
The supply of the Spirit is not
always at the level of your
need. It always surpasses
that. Even if you're at your
lowest point, the supply of the
Spirit of grace will be so
overwhelming that you will float
out of the valley.
But you must learn to respond to
the prompting. I've said so many
times that that sad feeling— not
every sad emotion is a
depression. Sometimes it is the
expression of the Holy Ghost
through your emotion that a
battle is approaching. Rise up!
Because Holy Spirit does not
just communicate to us through
words alone. Sometimes it
communicates through emotion.
He has emotion. Bible says that
do not grieve. You can only
grieve someone that has emotion.
So not every sad feeling is mood
swing. Be spiritual. That's why
many people are fully sunk into
depression because they never
understood the emotion of the
spirit. He's the one prompting
you to pray. Hallelujah!
Are you getting what I'm saying
here? He's the one prompting you
to pray. He awakens you. He
intimates you about what is—
sometimes you don't even know
the reason why you're praying.
I remember one time I was, I was
in my pastor's car driving from
one town to our base. We went
for a meeting. It was an
all-night meeting. So after the
meeting, we were coming back to
our base. It was an interstate
journey, and I was, I was seated
at the back with the kids. The
wife was seated beside him, and
you know, of course he was
driving. And we just got to a
particular spot, and I just have
the prompting to pray. You know,
this is me in my pastor's car.
I do not want to sound so
spiritual. I don't even know
that kind of a setting. I don't
want to appear as if I'm trying
to be spiritual. I'm in my
pastor's car. So I was
suppressing it, but the urge was
rising strong. I just yielded to
it and I began to pray in
tongues. It wasn't up to 10
minutes, we ran into an
accident. We hit a soldier.
Some of you have heard me tell
the story a number of times. We
hit a soldier. In fact, we
thought that the guy was dead.
You will never have met me if
not for the help of the Holy
Spirit. That was the first and
the only time guns, rifles,
about 6 or 7 of them were
pointed at us. And I was already
saying my last prayer, that God
have mercy, please let me make
heaven, please let me make
heaven, please forgive all my
sins. And Holy Spirit told
me, he said, if you had not
yielded to the prompting of the
Holy Spirit, something else
would have happened. I told you,
many times bad things happen to
good people because we allow the
devil to gain its parts before
we are awakened to the
consciousness. That there is
warfare.
So just imagine, imagine you,
you two people are, they are
racing to a direction. Let's say
you are running from here to,
uh, you're running from here to
Lekki Phase 1. Now you thought
that the person you are running
with is around you, but somehow
you've been distracted and the
person is already somewhere
around Chevron or Orchid, and
you are going to the same
direction, that person has head
Are you getting what I'm saying?
So learn to respond to the
promptings. Many of you, when
the Holy Spirit is prompting
you, you look around you, my
children is fine, everything is
fine, what is going on? Some of
you just feel like, why am I
feeling like this? What
happened? What happened?
Nothing happened now. I didn't
fight anybody. I don't have
offense in my heart. Why am I
feeling this way? Just go and
watch Sabinus' diary to lighten
the mood. Now you watch Sabinus,
you watch everything, that thing
is still hanging. You can only
dissipate such burden in the
place of prayer. And I'm telling
you, that never judge by
how you feel. Even when you
don't feel like praying, just
yield to his help. Because God
never planned that you have a
prayer life outside the Holy
Spirit. Not even a prayer life.
He never intended that you will
have any prayer moment. He said
all prayer always in the spirit.
So the Holy Spirit is always
there. Even when I sense the
burden in the bedroom, even when
I am in the toilet, there's
nowhere you find yourself, just
trust the Holy Spirit. Because
what gives potency to your
prayer is not the words you
speak, it is the utterance that
the Holy Spirit is supplying.
Some of the people that have the
funniest sound of tongue are the
most dangerous people.
Oh, glory to God! So you don't
judge potency by the
vocabularies. And I'm telling
you, see, we don't always speak
the same tongue. And I'm even
talking about myself. Sometimes
the tongue you hear me speak in
church is different from the one
that comes out of my mouth. In
the place of prayer. You know,
I was praying one day and the
person I was praying with had to
record. Now, this is many years
ago. I was still an
undergraduate. I think I was at
300 level. And the person had to
record the prayer. He said,
'Brother, I don't understand.
Listen to it.' He said the
person kept that prayer on their
phone for a very long time.
They use it for ringing tone.
Even me myself, I had all that.
Did this thing come out of my
mouth? It is you praying with
all the earnestness you can
gather in your heart. Glory to
God! The Holy Spirit also
supplies utterance. Now I'm
telling you, the ministry— what
the Spirit of God supplies,
what this spirit of grace and
supplication does to you
regarding prayer. So what's the
first thing? It prompts you.
Then the second thing is that it
supplies utterance. Acts chapter
2, Bible says that the Holy
Ghost gave them utterance, but
they did the speaking. They
spoke as the Holy Spirit gave
them utterance. So what the Holy
Spirit gives you is is
utterance. This utterance is
breath of the spirit. That is
where the power lies. The power
is not in the vocabulary, it is
in the breath that comes out of
your spirit. That breath is the
cry, utterance. And in this
utterance, it is only to your
understanding that this
utterance is not intelligible.
This utterance is intelligible
to the ears of God. Bible says
that the one who knows the
hearts of men— oh, praise God
forevermore! Let's go back to
Romans chapter 8. And he that
searcheth the hearts knows what
is in the mind of the Spirit,
because he maketh intercession
for the saints according to the
will of God. According to the
will of God. Now let me show you
something in the book of 1
Corinthians. Glory, glory,
glory to God. Verse 10: For to
us God revealed them through his
Spirit, for the Spirit searches
all things, even the depths of
God. Glory to God! The Spirit
does what? He searches all
things, even the depths of God.
The Holy Ghost knows the depths
of God's plan for your life.
Now you are there, you are
dreaming to have a dream year,
a dream year with a great job,
a dream year with your own
apartment where you are no
longer answerable to any lawyer,
a dream year where you now have
your SUV. And that is your
dream. Yeah, the Bible says the
Holy Spirit knows the depths of
God, because what is in your
mind are the surface things,
the surface plan of God for your
life, the one that your mind can
easily interpret. But I'm
telling you, there are depths to
God's plan for your life, and
Holy Spirit knows about all He
knows about all things.
Hallelujah! Praise God!
Say, the Holy Spirit— hey, come
on, louder! Say, the Holy Spirit
searches all things,
even the deep things of God. Oh
my God, the deep things of God,
the deep plans of God for my
life. Those are the utterances
supplied unto you in the place
of prayer. If you leave your
prayer life to your
understanding, you'll only be
asking for the things that your
mind can relate with, and you
can only ask for what you know.
Glory to God. Now just imagine,
just, just imagine that you,
you tell a woman, an old woman
that is an illiterate that lives
in a village that has never in
her life, never in her life had
an iPhone before, and you say
that, uh, Mama, which one will
you want, iPhone 17 or Nokia?
Do you know that if she's
familiar with Nokia, she will
definitely go for Nokia?
Because that is what he knows.
There are best things in God's
plan for your life you don't
know. So if you leave your
prayer life to what you're your
understanding can process, you
will miss the best things that
is in the plan of God for your
life.
And so when the Holy Spirit
supply utterance, this utterance
is communicating the deep things
unto God. It is an encrypted
conversation. Now Paul says in
Romans that God knows the
hearts. He knows the hearts
of men. He knows what is in the
mind of the spirit. The spirit
too knows what is in the mind of
God. Oh, you didn't get that?
Bible says in Romans 8 that the
spirit— I'm sorry, Romans
8:26-27 rather— that God knows
the mind of the spirits. He
knows the thoughts of the
spirits. In that utterance you
are speaking The God can pick
the information, he knows it.
Now where does the information
comes from? The information
comes from the research of the
Holy Spirit about God's plan for
your life. Let me give you an
example here. It is just like
Isaac is asking for venison.
His wife is the one that is
helping you to prepare the
venison. Rebecca knows Because
Rebecca was the one that created
the recipe that Isaac fell in
love with. She's been cooking
for Isaac long before they were
conceived. There's no way Jacob
would have beat the recipe of
his mother. Rebecca knows the
mind of Isaac. So Isaac says,
I want venison. The one who
knows the mind of Isaac prepares
it and handed it over. To Jacob
to present it to the father.
That is what the Holy Spirit
does. He knows the mind of the
father. He will give you the
expo that these are the things
that God has in plan for your
life. You are asking for a car,
but God will give you a factory.
So don't ask for those things.
Come and take this, get this,
present it to the father. You
can't say no to Praise God
forevermore. Glory to God. Oh,
what a sweet Holy Spirit! Why
won't you, why won't you respond
to this spirit of grace and
supplication?
For who among you knows— for who
among people knows the thoughts
of a person except the spirit of
the person that is in him? Who
also know the thoughts of God.
Who— so also the thoughts of
God, no one knows except the
Spirit of God. Nobody knows
except the Spirit of God. So
when the Holy Spirit gives you
utterance, it is in precision
concerning God's plan for your
life. You can't pray amiss when
you pray in the Spirit. It gives
you the utterance. The same
thing you are speaking, the same
vocabulary you are speaking when
you are asking for a particular
petition, it sounded the same
way you are asking for another
thing, but you are communicating
totally two different things.
Are you getting what I'm saying
here? Then the Spirit of God
gives you burden. It gives us
burden, especially for
intercession. He distributes
burden. I love something that
Paul says. He said that I may
know him, the power of his
resurrection The fellowship
of a suffering. So there are
times that the Holy Spirit will
share burdens with you, and
that's what I was talking about.
That is not every sad feeling
really mean that something bad
is going on in your life.
Sometimes it could be that God
is sensitizing you on something
that is about to happen, or God
wants you to intercede for
somebody. Glory to God. And the
last thing, it quickens us.
Let's see Psalm 80. This is one
of my favorite scriptures.
Psalm 80, verse 18. Verse 18,
it says— I love the KJV
translation of that verse. It
says, so will not we go back
from thee Quicken us and
we will call upon thy name.
Quicken us and we will call upon
thy name. Quicken us,
invigorate us, revive us. So you
can't call upon God except he
quickens you. See,
if you can go listen to this
message again and again and
you— your prayer life does not
pick up, I don't know what else
can help you. It is the Holy
Spirit that will help you. He
said, quicken us that we may
call upon you. And the way God
quickens us is by the spirit of
grace and supplication, which
means that he vitalizes us, he
energizes us in the place of
prayer. You will be so shocked
that you have missed so many
prayer opportunities because you
thought you were weak. If only
you could just yield to the Holy
Spirit even in that state of
weakness, and then you realize
the amount of energy that you
could dispense in the place of
prayer. It is the Holy Spirit,
it is not you. So you just learn
how to respond to the Spirit of
God. Tell your
neighbor, say, learn to respond.
Learn to respond. Be vulnerable
to the Holy Spirit. Stop
packaging to the Spirit of God.
Be vulnerable to God's Spirit.
Then stay there. Is that very
clear? Stay there. Never be in
haste. Sometimes, then Kenneth
Hagin said that sometimes it
could be after 30 minutes.
Sometimes it could be as long as
1 hour. Before he feels
that quickening, he'll stay
there. Is that very clear? This
is the most practical thing you
will hear from me today. If you
want to respond to the ministry,
to the supply of the Holy
Spirit, don't ask for his help
and walk away. Ask for his help
and stay there. Just stay there.
Even when that tongues sound
mechanical, Just stay there.
Is that very clear? Stay there.
Even when you don't feel like,
even when you feel it is forced,
just stay there and keep your
mouth moving. Keep your mouth
moving. Keep your mouth moving.
Oh, before you know what is
happening, you have stood up.
Before you know what is
happening, you're already pacing
the floor. Before you know what
is happening, you're already
scattering everywhere. But you
never get to that point if you
don't Stay there. Tell them,
say, stay there. Say, stay there
until the help comes. The Holy
Spirit helps us to pray and is
helping you today. He's the one
that helps us to pray
effectively. The Spirit of God
is helping us. Cobra hand.
Thank you for listening. For
enquiries, contact us on our
helpline +234 8104544689.
Go in this might.